{"Problem 1": {"problem": "A girl puts 5 letters in 5 evelopes randomly. In how many cases no letters is sent correctly?", "solution": "<step> You can consider problem is how many permutations of (1 2 3 4 5) that no number comes back to its own place. <\\step>\n<step> To solve the problem you could use inclusion exclusion theorem and calculate the following.\nNumber of all permutations is 5!. <\\step>\n<step>  Assume one is correct and on its right place, we can find this one C^{1}_{5} = 5 combinations, the rest is permutated in 4! ways.  <\\step>\n <step> Then we keep two in place with C^{2}_{5} ways, permutting the rest with 2!. <\\step>\n  <step> According to inclusion exclusion theorem we calculate the whole sum:\n<equation> 5! - C^{1}_{5} 4! + C^{2}_{5} 3! - C^{3}_{5} 2! + C^{4}_{5} 1! = 120 - 5*24 + 10*6 - 10*2 + 5*1 - 1*1 = 44 <\\equation>   <\\step>"}, "Problem 2": {"problem": "A block of mass m=2 kg is attached to a spring with spring constant k = 100 N/m. The block is pulled x=20 cm to the right of the spring's equilibrium position and released from rest. Find the maximum speed of the block.", "solution": "We will use the principle of conservation of energy. The potential energy of a spring is equal to P=1/2 kx^2. \nWhen we release the spring, this energy will be converted into kinetic energy until the midpoint, where all energy is kinetic. The formula for kinetic energy is E=1/2 mv^2.\nDue to conservation of energy, we know that the two values P and E must be equal. We apply algebraic operations to obtain v:\n1. 1/2 kx^2 = 1/2 mv^2\n2. kx^2 = mv^2\n3. k/m x^2 = v^2\n4. v = sqrt(k/m) x\n\nSubstituting the values, we get v = sqrt(100/2) * 0.2 = sqrt(2)."}, "Problem 3": {"problem": "COMBINATORIAL ANALYSIS\nProblem Set 1 Solutions (MIT, Fall 2021)\nProblem 1. Show that at any given moment of this semester, we can choose two\nstudents in our class having the same number of friends inside our class.\n", "solution": "Solution. Let S be the set of students in our class, and set n := |S|. If one student s0\ndoes not have any friend in the class, then each of the n \u2212 1 students in S \\ {s0\n} has\nat most n \u2212 2 friends in the class, and it follows by the PHP that two of the students\nin S \\ {s0\n} have the same number of friends. On the other hand, if each student has\nat least one friend, then the number of friends of each of the n students is a number in\n[n \u2212 1], and once again it follows from the PHP that two of them must have the same\nnumber of friends inside our class.\n"}, "Problem 4": {"problem": "Problem 2. Show that (n/3)n < n! < (n/2)n for every n \u2208 Z with n \u2265 6.\n", "solution": "Solution. First, note that (6/3)6 = 64 < 720 = 6! and 6! = 720 < 729 = (6/2)6.\nNow assume that n/3 n\n< n! < (n/2)n for some n \u2208 N with n \u2265 6. Recall from\ncalculus that the sequence (1+1/n)n increases and limn\u2192\u221e\nn\nn\n= e (the increasing\npart can be either taken for granted or proved using Bernoulli\u2019s inequality, namely,\n(1 + x)n \u2265 1 + nx for every x > \u22121). Therefore\nn\nn\nfor every n \u2265 2. From the right inequality of (0.1), we obtain that (n+1)n < 3nn, and\nso\nn + 1\n=\nn + 1\n(n + 1)n < (n + 1)\nn\nn\n< (n + 1)!,\nwhere the last inequality follows from our induction hypothesis. On the other hand,\nobserve that the left inequality of (0.1) ensures that 2nn < (n+1)n. As a consequence,\nwe obtain that\n(n + 1)! < (n + 1)\nn\nn\n=\nn + 1\nn + 1\n=\nn + 1\n,\nwhere the \ufb01rst inequality follows from our induction hypothesis.\n"}, "Problem 5": {"problem": "Problem 3. Consider the sequence (Fn\nobtained by setting F0\n= 1, and\nFn\nfor every n \u2265 2. Prove that 18211 divides Fn\nfor some n \u2208 N. [This\nis called the Fibonacci sequence and we will learn more about it throughout the course].\f", "solution": "2 F. GOTTI\nSolution. Since the set {(r1\n) | 0 \u2264 r1\n< 18211} has size 182112, it follows from\nthe PHP that there exist i, j \u2208 [182112 + 1] with i < j such that Fi\n\u2261 Fj\n(mod 18211). Then\n\u2212 Fi\n\u2212 Fj\n(mod 18211).\nIn a similar way, we can verify that Fi\u22122\n(mod 18211), and we can continue\nin this fashion until we obtain that 0 = F0\n\u2261 Fj\u2212i\n(mod 18211). Hence Fj\u2212i\nis a\nFibonacci number divisible by 18211.\n"}, "Problem 6": {"problem": "Problem 4. Let T be a triangle with two angles of 30\u25e6. Prove that T can be subdivided\ninto n smaller triangles similar to it for all n > 3.\n", "solution": "Solution. Let A, B, and C be the vertices of T.\nFor n = 4, consider the subdivision obtained by drawing the triangle EDK, where\nE, D, and K are the middle points of the segments AB, AC, and BC, respectively\n(see the top-left \ufb01gure below).\nFor n = 5, take E and D in the segment CB such that \u2220CAE = \u2220DAB = 30\u25e6. Now\ndraw the regular triangle AED, and then draw three segments from the centroid K\nof AED to its vertices. This gives us a subdivision of T into \ufb01ve triangles similar to\nitself (see the top-right \ufb01gure below).\nFor n = 6, take E and D in the segments AB and AC, respectively, so that\n|EB| = 1\n|AE| and |DC| = 1\n|AD|. Let K be the middle point of the segment ED.\nTake M and N in BC satisfying that |BM| = |MN| = |NC|. It is easy to check\nthat the triangulation one obtains by drawing the triangles EKM and KDN is a\nsubdivision of T into six triangles similar to itself (see the bottom \ufb01gure below).\nA\nB C\nD\nE\nK\nA\nB\nC\nD\nE\nK\nA\nB C\nD\nE K\nM N\nTaking the previous cases as base cases, we can proceed by induction. Assume that we\ncan \ufb01nd a desired subdivision of T for every k \u2208 4, n for some n \u2265 6. To subdivide T\ninto n + 1 triangles similar to itself, we can \ufb01rst subdivide T into n \u2212 2 \u2265 4 triangles\nsimilar to itself, and then we can subdivide one of the triangles of such a subdivision\ninto four triangles similar to T (as in the case when n = 4).\n"}, "Problem 7": {"problem": "Problem 5. For n \u2208 N and k \u2208 Z with 0 \u2264 k \u2264 n, let N(n, k) be the number of\nk-subsets of [n] that do not contain a pair of consecutive integers.\n(1) Prove that N(n, k) = n\u2212k+1\nk\n.\fCOMBINATORIAL ANALYSIS 3\n(2) Prove that n\nN(n, k) = Fn+2\n, where Fn+2\nis the (n + 2)-th term of the\nFibonacci sequence.\n", "solution": "Solution. (1) Let T(n, k) be the collection of k-subsets of [n] that do not contain a pair\nof consecutive integers. De\ufb01ne f : T(n, k) \u2192 [n\u2212k+1]\nk\nas follows: if S = {s1\n, . . . , sk\n} \u2208\nT(n, k) with s1\n< \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 < sk\n, then let f(S) = {s1\n\u2212 2, . . . , sk\n\u2212 k} and note that\nthe fact that S does not contain two consecutive integers ensures that |f(S)| = k.\nConversely, we can de\ufb01ne g: [n\u2212k+1]\nk\n\u2192 T(n, k) as follows: for any S = {s1\n, . . . , sk\n} \u2208\nk\n< \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 < sk\n, let g(S ) = {s1\n+ 2, . . . , sk\n+ k} and observe that\n< \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 < sk\n\u2264 n \u2212 k + 1 guarantees that g(S ) is a k-subset of [n] that does not\ncontain any two consecutive elements. Finally, one can readily check that f and g are\ninverses of each other, and so\nN(n, k) = |T(n, k)| =\nn \u2212 k + 1\nk\n.\n(2) It is clear that n\nN(n, k) is the size of the set T(n) consisting of all the subsets\nof [n] that do not contain a pair of consecutive integers. Let us show by induction\nthat |T(n)| = |Fn+2\n|. When n = 1 none of the two subsets of [1] contains a pair\nof consecutive elements, and so |T(1)| = 2 = F3\n. In addition, only one of the four\nsubsets of [2], namely {1, 2}, contains a pair of consecutive integers, and so |T(2)| =\n. Now suppose that, for some n \u2208 N, the equality |T(k)| = Fk+2\nholds for\nevery k \u2264 n. Observe that there are |T(n)| = Fn+2\nsubsets in T(n + 1) that do not\ncontain n + 1, those in T(n), and there are |T(n \u2212 1)| sets in T(n + 1) containing\nn + 1, those containing n + 1 that belong to T(n \u2212 1) when n + 1 is dropped. Hence\n|T(n + 1)| = |T(n)| + |T(n \u2212 1)| = Fn+1\n, which completes our inductive\nargument.\n"}, "Problem 8": {"problem": "Problem 6. Prove that\nk\u2208N\nk \u2212 1\ns \u2212 1\n2r \u2212 s\ns \u2212 1\nfor all r, s \u2208 N0\nby using a combinatorial argument.\n", "solution": "Solution. Suppose we have 2r delegates labeled 1, 2, . . . , 2r, from which we choose an\nodd-size committee p1\n, . . . , p2k\u22121\n, where p1\n< \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 < p2k\u22121\n, and then we choose a sub-\ncommittee of size s\u22121 consisting ot some of the committee members p2\n, . . . , p2k\u22122\n. We\ncan clearly do this\nk\u2208N\ndi\ufb00erent ways, which is the left-hand side of (0.2).\nLet us argue that the right-hand side of (0.2) also counts the pair of committees\nand sub-committees we have just described. This time we \ufb01rst choose a size-(s \u2212 1)\n, . . . , bs\u22121\n< \u00b7 \u00b7 \u00b7 < bs\u22121\n\u2264 2r \u2212 1 such that not two of\nthe labels b1\n, . . . "}, "Problem 9": {"problem": "Problem 7. What is the number of northeastern lattice paths from (0, 0) to (n, n) that\nonly touch the segment between (0, 0) and (n, n) at its endpoints?\n", "solution": ""}, "Problem 10": {"problem": "Problem 8. In the decimal representation of (\n\u221a\n\u221a\n3)2020, what digit is immediately\non the right of the decimal point?\f", "solution": "Solution. The number Cn\nof lattice paths from (0, 0) to (n, n) below (and possibly\nrepeatedly touching) the line y = x is Cn\nn\n, which is called the n-th Catalan\nnumber (see the solution of Exercise 4.24 in the textbook).\nLet En\nbe the set of lattice paths from (0, 0) to (n, n) whose \ufb01rst unit step is the\nvector (1, 0) and that only touch the line y = x at (0, 0) and (1, 1). By symmetry, the\nnumber we want to determine is 2|En\n|. Since the last unit step of each lattice path in\nEn\nmust be (0, 1), the set En\nis in bijection with the set Dn\u22121\nconsisting of all lattice\npaths from (1, 0) to (n, n \u2212 1) that do not go strictly above the line y = x \u2212 1: the\nbijections consists in dropping the \ufb01rst and the last steps. In addition, the set Dn\u22121\nis\nin bijection with the set Dn\u22121\nconsisting of all lattice paths from (0, 0) to (n\u22121, n\u22121):\nthe bijection consists in translating each lattice path by (\u22121, 0), a unit back. By the\nremark given in the previous paragraph,\n| = 2|Dn\u22121\n| = 2\n(n \u2212 1) + 1\nn \u2212 1\n=\nn\nn \u2212 1\n.\n"}}